Nicola Plant

Email: nicola@nicolaplant.co.uk n.j.plant@qmul.ac.uk Web: www.nicolaplant.co.uk www.github.com/nicolaplant

Nicola is a researcher, movement artist and coder about to finish a Ph.D in Media Art and Technology at the School of Electronic Engineering and Computer Science, Queen Mary University of London. Her research interests are human movement and expression, embodiment, intersubjectivity and the vicarious experience of empathy. Specialising in motion capture, interactive installation design and HCI, she makes movement-based interactive installations and environments, physical computing and electronics projects and real-time applications of technology for performance and installation. Her work has been presented at exhibitions and conferences worldwide. Currently she is resident at Fish Island Labs: a creative platform for emerging artists and technologists run by the Barbican Centre and The Trampery.

Nicola is a Research Assistant for Teaching London Computing Project, at the Education Lab at the School of Electronic Engineering and Computer Science, Queen Mary University of London. She develops teaching resources and applications and delivers courses and workshops to inspire and engage school teachers and students in computing and with new technologies. She is particularly interested in the interdisciplinarity of computer science education and creative fields, in terms of pedagogical practices but also as an anchor for diversity in computing and engineering. She has over 6+ years of experience in peer-to-peer computing teaching and leading creative coding workshops.

Professional Positions

2014-2015	Research Assistant: Teaching London Computing Project School of Electronic Engineering and Computer Science, Queen Mary University of London.
2014	Front End Developer for Mobile Publishing Platforms Short Internship with Kaldor, London.
2010-2013	Teaching Assistant for Undergraduate and Masters Modules: - Web Design and Authoring (UG & M) - Graphical User Interfaces (UG & M) - Procedural Programming (UG) - Algorithms and Data Structures in Object Orientated Programming (UG) School of Electronic Engineering and Computer Science, Queen Mary University of London.
2011-present	Senior Tutor and Workshop Leader: Creative Programming in Processing Popup Pixels, London.
2010	Research Placement: Untethered Human Computer Interaction Inition, London.
2006-2008	Technical Assistant, Audio Engineer & Video Editor Birmingham Conservatoire.
2005	Sound Technician Symphony Hall, Birmingham.

Academic Qualifications

2010 – 2015(present) **Ph.D Media and Arts Technology** (EPSRC Digital Economies DTC Scholarship)

Thesis: Intersubjectivity, Empathy and Nonverbal Interaction

Supervisors: Prof Pat Healey and Dr Martin Welton.

Cognitive Science Research Group,

School of Electronic Engineering and Computer Science,

Queen Mary University of London

2009 – 2010 MSc(Res) Media and Arts Technology

Untethered Human Computer Interaction: hosted by Inition (inition.co.uk)

School of Electronic Engineering and Computer Science,

Queen Mary University of London

2007 – 2008 MA Digital Arts in Performance

Birmingham Institute of Art and Design and Birmingham Conservatoire:

Birmingham City University

2004 – 2007 BSc (Hons) Music Technology

Birmingham Conservatoire and Technology Innovation Centre:

Birmingham City University

Technical Skills and Training

Skills

Programming Languages: Java // C++/OpenFrameworks // Python // MATLAB //

HTML5 // CSS3 // Javascript

Motion Capture: Autodesk MotionBuilder // Vicon Blade/iQ // Organic Motion Stage //

Phasespace // Microsoft Kinect // Leap Motion Controller

More: Max/MSP/Jitter // Physical Computing Projects using Arduino // Logic Pro //

ProTools // Final Cut Pro // Microsoft Office // ELAN

Teacher Training

Supervision of Undergraduate/Msc Projects & Teaching Your First Session Learning Institute, Queen Mary University of London.

Professional Training

Apple Certified Final Cut Pro and ProTools HD Training,

NTI Birmingham.

Composing for Film and Visual Media,

Birmingham Conservatoire.

Publications

Healey, P. G., Plant, N., Howes, C., & Lavelle, M. (2015). When Words Fail: Collaborative Gestures During Clarification Dialogues. In 2015 AAAI Spring Symposium Series.

Curzon, P., Plant, N., McOwan, P. W., & Meagher, L. R. (2014). *Introducing teachers to computational thinking using unplugged storytelling*. In Proceedings of the 9th Workshop in Primary and Secondary Computing Education (pp. 89-92). ACM.

Plant, N. and Healey, P. (2013) *Surface Tension*. ACM SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, CHI. Paris, France.

Plant, N. and Healey, P. (2012) *Empathy and Feedback in Conversations About Felt Experience*. The Interdisciplinary Workshop on Feedback Behaviors in Dialog. Portland, USA.

Plant, N. and Healey, P. (2012) *The Use of Gesture to Communicate about Felt Experiences*. The 16th Workshop on the Semantics and Pragmatics of Dialogue. Paris, France.

Exhibitions and Workshops

	1
2015	VR Installation: 'Movements of Being' Interfaces, Fish Islands Labs Showcase @ Barbican Centre, London.
2013	Installation: 'Surface Tension' ACM SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, Paris.
2012	Installation: 'Headache: A Study of Expressive Gesture' Digital Shoreditch Festival, London.
2012	Workshop Leader: 'Conductive Textiles and Thermochromic Inks' Central Saint Martins, London.
2011	Workshop Leader: 'T.Hack with G.Hack' Space Studios, London.
2011	Collaborative Installation: 'Sound Mapping London Tea Houses' London Design Festival, V&A Museum, London.
2011	Interactive Installation: 'Mirror Being' Digital Shoreditch Festival, London.
2011	Workshop Leader: 'Just a Switch' V&A Musuem, London.
2011	Collaborative Installation: 'Threads and Yarns' Wellcome Trust 75 th Anniversary Symposium, V&A Museum, London.
2008	Live Electronics and Media Installations: 'The Architect' & 'The Materialisation of Sound' BIAD Degree Show, Birmingham, UK.
2008	Performance: 'Faceless, Trapped by Technology' New Generation Arts Festival, Birmingham, UK.
2007	Live Electronics Performance: 'LRRH' Technology in Performance Concert, Birmingham Conservatoire, UK.